producttesting.uk.com 2018-12-05

# privacy and cookie policy

### **Privacy & Cookie Policy**

Last updated: 23.07.2018

This Privacy Policy (together with our terms of use) sets out the basis on which any personal data you provide to us, will be processed.

For your information, this website Product Testing UK (our site) is operated and wholly owned by Submission Technology Ltd., registered in England with the company number 4456811.

For the purposes of the EU General Data Protection Regulation (2016), Submission Technology Ltd. are the registered data controller with the Information Commissioner’s Office (ICO); our registration number is Z7981900.

Product Testing UK processes your data to notify you if you've been selected as a product tester, to send you the latest promotional offers by email if you opt-in to receive Product Testing UK emails, and to share your data with third parties if you opt-in to receive their services or direct marketing. We also process your personal data when you contact us with queries about your account or the site. 

If you have any questions regarding this policy, please contact our Data Protection Officer [here](mailto:dpo@submissiontechnology.co.uk). If you have a query about your account, please contact our customer service team [here](mailto:info@producttesting.uk.com). 

**When You Register**

To register an account, we will ask you to provide your first, last name, your date of birth, your email address, your mobile phone number, and your postal address.

  * We use your first and last name to identify you and to personalise your experience;
  * We use your date of birth to confirm that you are over 18 years old, as per our Terms & Conditions of the site;
  * We use your email address to send you a welcome email and, if you provide your opt-in consent, relevant marketing by email from Product Testing UK. We will also use your email address to contact you if you are selected as a product tester;
  * We use your mobile phone number to contact you if you are selected as a product tester; and,
  * We use your postal address to ensure you are a resident of the UK, as per our Terms & Conditions of the site, and sometimes to show you relevant opportunities in your area.

As part of our Terms & Conditions, you must be able to provide a review of your experience if you are selected as a product tester. By signing up to Product Testing UK you are confirming that you can provide a written review, video review and photos, and are giving permission for us to publish these details on our site. You have the right to request removal of this information at any time _._ We have a legitimate interest to publish all reviews provided to us to promote the third parties we market on our Site. As such, written reviews, video reviews and photographs provided to us by selected shoppers, along with the first name, last name and town of residence of the shopper, will be published on producttesting.uk.com in our Review Room and on our Social Media profiles.

Once you register with Product Testing UK you will receive a welcome email and, if you opt-in, regular newsletters packed with great prizes and opportunities including third party offers. If you do not want to receive these emails, you can click the unsubscribe link at the bottom of our emails or adjust your preferences in your account. The categories we advertise in our emails are as follows:

Retail

| 

  * Online retail
  * General stores
  * Automotive (including dealerships and accessories)
  * Property
  * Home furnishings
  * Home improvement
  * Fashion and clothing
  * Telecoms and utilities

---|---  
  
Finance

| 

  * Pensions
  * Loans, credit cards and mortgages
  * Investments & savings
  * Regulated claims management

Insurance

| 

  * Home
  * Car
  * Travel
  * Pet
  * Personal
  * PPI
  * Other insurances

Travel

| 

  * Holidays
  * Hotel
  * Airlines
  * Travel booking

Lifestyle

| 

  * Health & Well-being
  * Fitness
  * Charities
  * Media & publishing companies
  * Leisure
  * Gaming
  * Legal Services
  * Educational institutions
  * Gambling
  * Recruitment, Careers & Jobs

**Third Party Offers**

Once you have signed up to Product Testing UK, you will be invited to sign up to various third party offers. These are **optional,** you do not have to sign up to these offers to complete your entry, simply select ‘no’ or ‘not interested’ on each offer.

These offers are provided by our carefully selected clients. It is our duty to always be transparent with you which is why we will always tell you who you are sharing your data with. Please be mindful of the fact that we do not accept any liability or responsibility for the marketing offers you sign up to with our clients and their subcontractors and therefore we encourage you to read their Terms & Conditions and Privacy Policies that apply. These documents should contain contact details of our client’s Data Protection Officer, the period of time that your data will be stored by our client, the existence of your rights under the GDPR, the right to lodge a complaint with a Supervisory Authority, and the existence of automated decision making. These will also contain details of how to unsubscribe from third party marketing communications. Please note, if you choose to receive marketing from third parties listed on Product Testing UK, it is your responsibility to opt-out of this marketing if you no longer wish to receive communications from them.

**Technical Information**

With regard to each of your visits to our site, we may automatically collect the following information:

Technical information, including:

  * The Internet Protocol (IP) address used to connect your computer to the Internet;
  * Your login information if you choose for a quicker sign in process;
  * Browser type and version to provide you with an optimized viewing experience;
  * Time zone setting to ensure we provide you with the most appropriate offers;
  * Browser plug-in types and versions; and,
  * Operating system and platform.

Information about your visit, including:

  * The full Uniform Resource Locators (URL) clickstream to, through and from our site (including the date and time);
  * Products you viewed or searched for;
  * Page response times and download errors;
  * Lengths of visits to certain pages;
  * Page interaction information (such as scrolling, clicks and mouse-overs);
  * Methods used to browse away from the page; and
  * Any phone number used to call our customer service team if you linked to our site from another website, the address of that website, and, if you linked to the site from a search engine, the address of that search engine and the search term you used.

We have a legitimate interest to process this data because it helps us tailor and optimize your experience on the Site.

**Customer Service**

If you contact our customer service team, we will collect your first and last name, your email address or phone number (whichever one you used to contact us), your account number (if applicable) and your message. We have a legitimate interest to keep this data for all the time that you are a customer with us and 12 months after. This is to ensure that we can answer any future queries you may have as quickly as possible.

At times, we may need to verify your age or identity. In this instance we will ask for a proof of identification proportionate to that of your request e.g. a utility bill, or if needed, a copy of your driving license. When you send these forms of identification through, only our customer service team will be able to view these and once they have verified your identity or your age, the copy of your identification will be securely destroyed. We never store this information. 

**Product Testing UK further uses your information to:**

  * Enhance, modify, personalise or otherwise improve our services/ communications for the benefit of our users;
  * Maintain suppression or opt-out lists that we may share with third-parties so that a user is not contacted when the user has asked not to be;
  * Augment information by supplementing it with data from other sources to determine the effectiveness of promotional campaigns and advertising;
  * Track online behaviour to tailor advertising;
  * Respond to legal inquiries, or to establish or exercise our legal rights or defend against legal claims or when we determine it is necessary to comply with applicable laws or regulations; where permitted by applicable law, we will provide you with an e-mail notice, and opportunity to challenge the applicable subpoena/request prior to disclosure of any Information; and
  * Assist with site operation and other communication services, share information with third-parties, including our vendors and contractors. 

The law on data protection sets out a number of different reasons for which a company may collect and process your personal data. We rely on your consent, our legitimate interest and at times, our legal obligations.

**Consent**

In specific situations, we can collect and process your data with your consent. We collect your consent when applicable law (including but not limited to The Privacy and Electronic Communications (EC Directive) Regulations 2003 and the EU General Data Protection Regulation) requires it.

For example, when you tick a box to receive Product Testing UK email newsletters. Or when you opt-in to receive electronic communications from third parties. Or when you opt-in to receive messages from the ManyChat Bot on Facebook. 

When collecting your personal data, we’ll always make clear to you which data is necessary in connection with a particular service and who your data may be passed to. You can withdraw your consent at anytime. 

Users of our Site are required to be at least 18 years old, and any user under 18 is not an authorised user. We will never knowingly collect any personal information about children under the age of 18. If we obtain actual knowledge that it has collected personal information about a child under the age of 18, that information will be immediately deleted from our database.

**Legal compliance**

If the law requires us to, we may need to collect and process your data. 

For example, we can pass on details of people involved in fraud or other criminal activity.

**Legitimate interest**

In specific situations, we require your data to pursue our legitimate interests in a way which might reasonably be expected as part of offering our service and which does not materially impact your rights, freedom or interests.

For example, if you are selected as a product tester, we’ll use your postal or email address to send you your gift card/reward or product to test. 

We will also use your data to set you up an account so we can keep track of the offers you have signed up to in case you experience a problem with our site and we need to fix it, or you have a query about our site and we need to answer it. We also monitor our members’ accounts for fraudulent activity, for example, by looking out for duplicate entries/accounts which is against the Terms & Conditions of our site.

If you register your interest with a third party offer on our site that states you will receive a call, we will pass your telephone number (that you used to sign up to our site with) to the third party so one of their representatives can contact you regarding the offer, so long as your phone number is not registered with the Telephone Preference Service (TPS). We will always tell you in the offer that, by registering your interest, you will receive a call. 

Product Testing UK contain links to third party websites only as a convenience, and the inclusion of a link on our Site does not imply endorsement of the linked third party website by us. If you provide any personal information through any such third-party website, your transaction will occur on the third party’s website (not the Site) and the personal information you provide will be collected by, and controlled by the Privacy Policy and Terms & Conditions of that third party.

Product Testing UK holds your data in a UK database and only our highly trained and trusted staff can access your data on a need-to-know basis.  

If you wish to contact us regarding your data, please see Section 5.

We only disclose your data to third parties if you have opted in to receive their services or direct marketing. Please be mindful of the fact that we do not accept any liability or responsibility for the marketing offers you sign up to with our clients and therefore we encourage you to read their Terms & Conditions and Privacy Policies that apply. You should be aware that, in some instances, our clients might be based in countries outside the European Union whose laws provide for a different standard of protection for your personal data than that provided under EU Law. In such circumstance Product Testing UK will have in place contractual arrangements which will require your data to be transferred to the same standards as EU Law.

If you choose to sign up to receive emails from Product Testing UK, your name and email address will be passed to our 3rd party email service provider, Get Response. You can read their privacy policy and how they look after your data [here](https://www.getresponse.co.uk/email-marketing/gb-legal/privacy.html) **.  **

Except as provided above, under certain circumstances the force of law may require the provision of information to the legal authorities. In order to maintain the integrity of its website and safeguard the interests of its subscribers Product Testing UK will comply with any such legally binding request.

**                Right to Access**

You can access your data processed by us at any time. We will confirm what data is being processed, provide you with a copy of your data in addition to confirming your data rights.

If you wish to access your data, please submit a Subject Access Request (“SAR”) to our Data Protection Officer using reasonable means. If you make the request by email, the Data Protection Officer will provide your information in a commonly used electronic format unless you instruct them otherwise. Your request will remain confidential.

When making your request, please include:

  * Your full name and email address;
  * The website that you signed up to; and,
  * Details of the specific information you require and any relevant dates.

If we are unable or unwilling to agree to the request, we must inform you without undue delay and at the very latest within one month of receipt of your access request, why we have refused the request and that you have the right to complain to the supervisory authority.

Your request will be free of charge, unless “manifestly unfounded or excessive”.

               **Right to Rectification**

If at any point you believe the information we process on you is incorrect, you may at any time amend or update your data by visiting Product Testing UK, login and click on 'My Account'. There you will find a panel where you can amend or update your details. Alternatively, you can contact our customer service team via email [info@producttesting.uk.com](mailto:info@producttesting.uk.com) who will amend your details for you. 

               **Right to Erasure**

Please send your request for erasure to our Data Protection Officer by any reasonable means. If you request for your data to be erased, then we will confirm whether this can take place and the next steps that we will take. If we cannot erase your data, we will explain why and confirm any actions required to allow us to do so.

               **Restrict Processing**

If you make a restriction request, we will still store a copy of your data but cannot use this. We will inform you if the restriction needs to be lifted. You can make this request by email. If you request for your data to be restricted, we will confirm whether this can take place and the next steps that we will take. If we cannot restrict your data, we will explain why and confirm any actions required to allow us to do so.

               **Object to Processing**

You can object to the processing of your data at any time. This right will only apply if we are using your data in relation to a legitimate interest. If you object, we will no longer process your data unless we have a compelling and legitimate reason not to do so (e.g. a legal obligation). In this case, you will be informed why we cannot stop processing your data.

               **Data Portability**

You can request for us to transfer your data to another entity or person, where we are processing your data with your consent or in accordance with a contract. This will only apply to information which is processed by automated means (e.g. by a computer). Where feasible, we will send your data directly to another entity or person.

In exercising any of your rights, we will endeavour to act without undue delay but no later than one month. We will need to confirm your identity before completing any action on your behalf and reserve the right to not complete action until we are satisfied that it is you that is making the request. If we cannot complete your request, we will inform you within one month and explain why.

If you are not satisfied with our response or believe we are processing your personal data not in accordance with the law you can make a complaint to the UK Supervisory Authority, the Information Commissioner’s Office (ICO). You can contact the ICO through their website:<https://ico.org.uk/concerns/> or by telephone: 0303 123 1113.

As per our retention policy, we will keep your data for 12 months from your most recent activity in your account, unless you notify us otherwise. After 12 months of inactivity, your account will be deleted and you will be unsubscribed from any Product Testing UK marketing activity.

When you unsubscribe from marketing from Product Testing UK we will store your name and email address on our email database hosted by our third party provider to ensure we do not contact you again. This database can only be accessed by a select few of our highly trained staff.

At any time, you have the right to:

  * Update your data
  * Close your account
  * Request a copy of the data we hold on you in an easy to read format
  * Restrict or object to the processing of your data
  * Be forgotten i.e., have your data erased from our database and that of any associated 3rd parties
  * Lodge a data protection complaint with the Supervisory Authority.

Please see **Section 5** for further information on your rights.

You can unsubscribe from Product Testing UK marketing emails by clicking on the unsubscribe link at the bottom of the email or you can unsubscribe through your account. You will need to log in to unsubscribe and select from the options available. Please allow up to 48 hours for changes to take effect.

To stop push notifications, you can right click on the notification and click disable if you are on a desktop computer. If you are on a mobile device there will be an option within your browser settings to disable or stop website notifications.

To delete your account, please sign in to your account and select ‘delete account’. Please allow 48 hours for the changes to take place.

Product Testing UK is committed to protecting the security of your personal information. We protect your information with security measures under the laws that apply and we meet international standards. We use a variety of technologies to help protect your personal information from unauthorised access, use, or disclosure.

We apply segmented access controls so only our highly trained and trusted staff can access your data on a need to know basis. All systems and data are located in the UK in controlled and secure areas.

Unfortunately, the Internet is not a 100% secure medium for communication and, accordingly, Product Testing UK cannot guarantee the security of any information you send to Product Testing UK via the Internet.

In the event of a data breach that affects your data, we will notify you by email. 

To access your Product Testing UK account you must type in the correct password. It is your responsibility to keep this password secure; consider changing your password every 3-6 months. Ideally your password should be at least 8 characters long, contain at least one capital letter, some numbers and a special character (e.g. ? ! , _) and should not be disclosed to anyone.

Product Testing UK is not responsible for any loss or damage you or others may suffer as a result of the loss of confidentiality of your data.

In the event of updates to our service that materially expand the sharing or use of your personal information in ways not already disclosed to you, we will notify you by email and update this privacy policy accordingly. We will gain your consent for processing activities where necessary.

**Our postal address**

Product Testing UK

The Beater House

Turkey Mill

Maidstone

Kent

ME14 5PP

**Product Testing UK Customer Service**

Email address: [info@producttesting.uk.com](mailto:info@producttesting.uk.com)

Telephone number: +44 (0)20 7183 1653

**Data Protection Officer**

Submission Technology Ltd

Telephone number: +44 (0)20 7183 5039             

Email: [dpo@submissiontechnology.co.uk](mailto:dpo@submissiontechnology.co.uk)

We use cookies and other storage technologies on our site, Product Testing UK (our site, or our sites), to provide you with the best experience when you browse our website and to improve our site and its contents. By continuing to browse the site, you are agreeing to our use of cookies and other storage technologies.

A cookie is a small file of letters and numbers that we store on your browser or the hard drive of your computer if you agree. Other storage technologies you may come across include web beacons and pixels. A web beacon is an often-transparent graphic image that is placed on our website or in an email that is used to monitor the behaviour of users visiting our sites or receiving our emails. Web beacons are usually used in conjunction with cookies to check that you can see our content. A pixel refers to the code that is placed on our website that triggers a cookie. A pixel is essentially an image but instead of calling an image to be displayed, it calls an application on a media buying platform that will cause a cookie to be downloaded to your browser, if your browser settings allow.

To find out how to opt out of the collection and use of your information via storage technologies, see our section below on  **Blocking or Declining Cookies.**

For further information about behavioural advertising, cookies and other storage technologies, and the steps you can take to protect your privacy online visit <http://optout.aboutads.info/?c=2#!/> or <http://www.youronlinechoices.eu/>

We use the following cookies:

  * **Strictly necessary cookies.**  These are cookies that are required for the operation of our website. They include, for example, cookies that enable you to log into secure areas of our website.
  * **Analytical/performance cookies.  **They allow us to recognise and count the number of visitors and to see how visitors move around our website when they are using it. This helps us to improve the way our website works, for example, by ensuring that users find what they are looking for easily.
  * **Functionality cookies.**  These are used to recognise you when you return to our website. This enables us to personalise our content for you, greet you by name and remember your preferences (for example, your choice of language or region).
  * **Targeting cookies.**  These cookies record your visit to our website, the pages you have visited and the links you have followed. We will use this information to make our website and the advertising displayed on it more relevant to your interests. We may also share this information with third parties for this purpose.

**Strictly Necessary Cookies**

These cookies are necessary for the website to function and cannot be switched off in our systems. They are usually only set in response to actions made by you which amount to a request for services, such as setting your privacy preferences, logging in or filling in forms.

You can set your browser to block or alert you about these cookies, but some parts of the site will not then work. These cookies do not store any personally identifiable information.

Cookies used:

Cookie Name

| 

Provider

| 

Description

| 

Expiry

| 

Type  
  
---|---|---|---|---  
  
SERVERID

| 

r3engage.com

| 

This cookie is usually used for load balancing. It identifies the server that delivered the last page to the browser. Associated with the HAProxy Load Balancer software

| 

Session

| 

HTTP  
  
__cfduid

| 

Onesignal.com

| 

This cookie is used to identify individual clients behind a shared IP address and apply security settings on a per-client basis. If you were in a coffee shop where several infected computers are using the same IP address but your device is secure, this cookie allows you to log in but not others.

| 

1 year

| 

HTTP  
  
**Performance Cookies**

These cookies allow us to count visits and traffic sources so we can measure and improve the performance of our site. They help us to know which pages are the most and least popular and see how visitors move around the site.

All information these cookies collect is aggregated and therefore anonymous. If you do not allow these cookies we will not know when you have visited our site, and will not be able to monitor its performance.

Cookies used:

Cookie Name

| 

Provider

| 

Description

| 

Expiry

| 

Type  
  
---|---|---|---|---  
  
_gat

| 

Producttesting.uk.com

| 

This cookie name is associated with Google Universal Analytics, it is used to ensure efficiency - limiting the collection of data on high traffic sites.

| 

Session

| 

HTTP  
  
_gid

| 

This cookie name is associated with Google Universal Analytics. This is a new cookie used to store and update a unique value for each page visited.

| 

Session

| 

HTTP  
  
_ga

| 

This cookie name is associated with Google Universal Analytics. This cookie is used to distinguish unique users by assigning a randomly generated number as a client identifier. It is included in each page request in a site and used to calculate visitor, session and campaign data for the sites analytics reports.

| 

2 Years

| 

HTTP  
  
_qca

| 

This cookie collects anonymous data on the user’s visits to the website, such as the number of visits, average time spent on the website and what pages have been loaded with the purpose of generating reports for optimising the website content.

| 

1 year

| 

HTTP  
  
p.gif

| 

Typekit.net

| 

Unclassified

| 

Session

| 

Pixel  
  
**Targeting Cookies**

These cookies may be set through our site by our advertising partners. They may be used by those companies to build a profile of your interests and show you relevant adverts on other sites.

These cookies are based on uniquely identifying your browser and internet device. If you do not allow these cookies, you will experience less targeted advertising but equally you may not be able to experience the site fully.

Cookies used:

Cookie Name

| 

Provider

| 

Description

| 

Expiry

| 

Type  
  
---|---|---|---|---  
  
id

| 

doubleclick.net

| 

This cookie is used to improve advertising. Some common applications are to target advertising based on what's relevant to a user, to improve reporting on campaign performance, and to avoid showing ads the user has already seen.

| 

90 days

| 

HTTP  
  
mc

| 

quantserve.com

| 

Collects data on the user’s visits to the website, such as what pages have been loaded. The registered data is used for targeted ads.

| 

5 years

| 

HTTP  
  
Lang

| 

syndication.twitter.com

| 

This cookie is used to store language preferences, potentially to serve up content in the stored language.

| 

Session

| 

HTTP  
  
Ads/ga-audiences

| 

Google.com

| 

Used by Google AdWords to re-engage visitors that are likely to convert to customers based on the visitor’s online behaviour across the website.

| 

Session

| 

Pixel  
  
B

| 

Yahoo.com

| 

Collects anonymous data related to the user’s website visits, such as the number of visits, average time spent on the website and what pages have been loaded. The registered data is used to categorise the users’ interest and demographical profiles with the purpose of customising the website content depending on the visitor.

| 

1 year

| 

HTTP  
  
Collect

| 

Google-analytics.com

| 

Used to send data to Google Analytics about the visitor’s device and behaviour. Tracks the visitor across devices and marketing channels.

| 

Session

| 

Pixel  
  
fr

| 

Facebook.com

| 

Used by Facebook to deliver a series of advertisement products from third party advertisers.

| 

3 months

| 

HTTP  
  
spp.pl

| 

Analytics.yahoo.com

| 

This is a Yahoo pixel that tracks the performance of advertising campaigns. It helps with creating new audiences for retargeting and tracking website conversions and user behaviour.

| 

Session

| 

Pixel  
  
tr

| 

Facebook.com

| 

When a user visits our website and makes an action (for example, clicking on one of our ads), the Facebook Pixel placed on our website is activated and in turn triggers a cookie to send your action or Event Data to Facebook.

The cookie may also transfer your name, email address, phone number, date of birth or gender in a hashed format to Facebook. Facebook refers to this hashed data as Contact Information. (Hashed data is the processing of data in such a way that it cannot be attributed to a specific individual, usually, without the use of additional information.)

Your Contact Information is matched to the Event Data and is used to create a Custom Audience. A Custom Audience is a list of users that are grouped together by common Event Data.

Facebook will examine numerous data points of the Custom Audience and then build audiences similar to those users called a Look a Like Audience. Those users will then be shown ads that we think will be of interest to them. Your data is not passed on to any third parties other than Facebook.

| 

Session

| 

Pixel  
  
Onesignal-pageview-count

| 

Producttesting.uk.com

| 

Unclassified

| 

Session

| 

HTML  
  
ci_session_id

| 

Producttesting.uk.com

| 

Unclassified

| 

2 years

| 

HTTP  
  
Lang

| 

Syndication.twitter.com

| 

This cookie is used to store language preferences, potentially to serve up content in the stored language.

| 

Session

| 

HTTP  
  
APISID

| 

Google.com

| 

These are a range of cookies used by Google to improve your user experience and keep your data secure. Preference cookies are typically used to store user preferences, such as your preferred region, language, font size etc.; security cookies that encrypt the data users enter into online forms to prevent data from being stolen; process cookies which help the user navigate our site; advertising cookies to make advertising more engaging for users and more valuable to publishers and advertisers; session state cookies to improve the user browsing experience by analysing how many times a user visits a page and whether users receive error messages from certain pages; and, analytics cookies which are sent as part of the Google Analytics tool which helps us understand how users engage with our websites.

See Google’s privacy policy: <https://www.google.com/intl/en/policies/privacy/> and the types of cookies used by Google: <https://www.google.com/policies/technologies/types/> for more information.

| 

2 years

| 

HTTP  
  
SSID  
  
NID  
  
SAPISID  
  
HSID  
  
SID

| 

Youtube.com

| 

We embed videos from YouTube and by doing this it may set cookies on your computer once you click on the YouTube video player.

These cookies help track the number of views for a particular video. The PREF cookie will track user preferences and serve up related content or adverts within an embedded YouTube video.

Read more at YouTube’s embedding videos [information page](https://support.google.com/youtube/answer/171780?hl=en-GB). Visit YouTube’s privacy guidelines at <https://www.youtube.com/t/privacy_guidelines>

| 

2 years

| 

HTTP  
  
HSID

| 

2 years  
  
Demographics

| 

2 years  
  
VISITOR_INFO1_LIVE

| 

8 months  
  
PREF

| 

8 months  
  
APISID

| 

2 years  
  
SSID

| 

2 years  
  
LOGIN_INFO

| 

2 years  
  
YSC

| 

Session  
  
SAPISID

| 

2 years  
  
datr

| 

Facebook.com

| 

This is a verification cookie used to ensure your Facebook account is not fraudulent if you choose to sign in to your account via Facebook. It is also used to track users who do not sign in via Facebook but visit Facebook sites.

| 

2 years

| 

HTTP  
  
Lu

| 

This cookie is set the first time a user visits facebook.com and is used to identify the browser – it helps protect people using public computers.

| 

2 years

| 

HTTP  
  
_utmz

| 

Twitter.com

| 

This is one of the four main cookies set by the Google Analytics service which enables us to track visitor behaviour and measure site performance. This cookie identifies the source of traffic to the site - so Google Analytics can tell us where visitors came from when arriving on the site. The cookie has a life span of 6 months and is updated every time data is sent to Google Analytics.

| 

2 years

|   
  
_utma

| 

This is one of the four main cookies set by the Google Analytics service which enables us to track visitor behaviour and measure site performance. This cookie lasts for 2 years by default and distinguishes between users and sessions. It is used to calculate new and returning visitor statistics. The cookie is updated every time data is sent to Google Analytics. The lifespan of the cookie can be customised by website owners.

| 

2 years

| 

HTTP  
  
Remember_checked

| 

These cookies are used when integrating twitter feeds into our site's pages and to allow the sharing of content. They log you into your twitter account if you choose to stay logged in. Visit Twitter’s use of cookies page for more information at <https://help.twitter.com/en/rules-and-policies/twitter-cookies>

| 

2 years

| 

HTTP  
  
Auth_token

| 

15 years  
  
Twll

| 

2 years  
  
Secure_session

| 

15 years  
  
Guest_id

| 

2 years  
  
**Blocking or Declining Cookies**

If you don't want us to store cookies on your device, you can block cookies. Blocking cookies can prevent some pages from displaying correctly, or you might get a message from one of our sites letting you know that you need to allow cookies to view that site.

Please note, if you choose to turn off online behavioural advertising you will still see advertising on the internet. However, it does mean that the advertising you see may not be tailored to your likely interests or preferences on the web browser you are currently using.

                **Internet Explorer:**

  1. In Internet Explorer, select the  **tools**  button and then select  **internet options**
  2. Select the  **privacy tab**  and under  **Settings**  either: 
    1. Select  **advanced**  and choose if you want to allow, block or be prompted for first party and third party cookies; or,
    2. Move the slider to the top to block all cookies (or the bottom to allow all cookies), and then select OK.

**Google Chrome:**

  1. Click the chrome menu on the browser toolbar
  2. Select  **Settings**
  3. Click  **Show advanced settings**
  4. In the  **‘Privacy and Security’**  section, click the  **Content**  settings button
  5. In the  **‘Cookies’**  section, you can change to your preferred setting.

If you use another browser, visit <http://www.youronlinechoices.com/uk/five-top-tips> for more information on how you can opt-out of the collection and use of information for targeted advertising.
